Finding Aid for Prison Creative Arts Project collection, 1992-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Prison Creative Arts Project collection 1992-2013
Prison Creative Arts Project.
2010177 Aa 2
Collected creative writing publications and recorded theatrical productions of adults and youth incarcerated in correctional facilities across the state of Michigan. Also included poetry and photographs of Michigan high school students.
2.4 linear feet
6 GB online
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by William (Buzz) Alexander (donor no. 10221 ) in August 2010. Additional material donated in multiple accessions.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Prison Creative Arts Project was established in 1990 by University of Michigan professor Buzz Alexander to work with incarcerated Michigan adults and youths in the creative arts, including theater, creative writing, art, dance and music.
Anthologies of poetry and short stories produced in Michigan correctional facilities represent the bulk of the manuscript portion of the collection. Among manuscript material also found scrapbooks and photo albums. The audiovisual portion of the collection contains recorded theatrical productions. The collection is organized into four series: Creative Writing, Performing Arts, Prison Creative Arts Project Material, and Audiovisual Material.
Subjects:
Alexander, William, 1938-; Arts in prison--Michigan.; Community arts projects--Michigan.; High school students' writings--Michigan--Detroit.; Juvenile delinquents--Rehabilitation--Michigan.; Prisoners--Education--Michigan.; Prisoners as artists--Michigan.; Prison Creative Arts Project.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Alexander, William, 1938-; Art exhibitions--Michigan.; Arts in prison--Michigan.; Community arts projects--Michigan.; Prison Creative Arts Project.; Prisoners--Education--Michigan.; Prisoners as artists--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Digital file formats.; DVDs.; Playbills.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Creative writing
  The Creative Writing series includes publications, mostly anthologies of poems, produced by members of PCAP workshops in correctional and training facilities across the state. Also included works by Detroit high school students and unidentified youth programs. Material is organized in alphabetical order of names of individual correctional facilities. Name of individual creative writing group, workshop, or a publisher, and the year of publication are indicated after each title.
  - Correctional facilities
    - Adrian Temporary Correctional Facility (Adrian, Mich.) (Box 1)
      - An anthology of writing Creative Writing Workshop, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Boysville Correctional Facility (Clinton, Mich.)
      - Paulus Hall creative writing anthology Unidentified group, 2004 (Box 1)
      - Young words: an anthology Creative Writing Workshop, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Boysville Detention Center (Clinton, Mich.)
      - Words for hope Unidentified group, undated (Box 1)
    - Camp Cassidy Lake (Chelsea, Mich.)
      - Our Saturday morning (wo)men's club Creative Writing Workshop, 2009 (Box 1)
    - Camp Valley (Ypsilanti, Mich.)
      - Thirst for life: and anthology of sisterhood Creative Writing Workshop, 2008 (Box 1)
    - Cooper Street Correctional Facility (Jackson, Mich.)
      - Creative minds: writing beyond imagination line Creative Writing Workshop, 2006 (Box 1)
      - Speak(easy): an anthology of creative writing 2010-2011 (Box 1)
    - G. Robert Cotton Correctional Facility (Jackson, Mich.)
      - Anthology of mind and pen Creative Writing Workshop, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Hiawatha Correctional Facility (Kincheloe, Mich.)
      - Concertina: an anthology of poetry Weekend Workshop, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Huron Valley Correctional Facility (Ypsilanti, Mich.)
      - Burning ideas Huron Valley Writers, 2003 (Box 1)
      - Thinking out loud: mixed emotions The Huron Valley Creative Arts Workshop, 2003 (Box 1)
      - Epigraph: poets and presidents Creative Writing Workshop, 2007 (Box 1)
      - Behind these solitary walls, a symphony of life The Sisters with Unique Minds, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Lakeland Correctional Facility (Coldwater, Mich.)
      - Pivotal Moments Lakeland Poetry Workshop, 2004 (Box 1)
      - I used to wear a mask; laugh now cry later The Lakeland Writers, 2006 (Box 1)
    - Macomb Correctional Facility (Lenox, Mich.)
      - Echoing thoughts The Writer's Block, 2011 (Box 1)
      - Peer poetry The Writer's Block, 2011 (Box 1)
      - Reaching with a pen The Writer's Block, 2011 (Box 1)
    - Mound Correctional Facility (Detroit, Mich.)
      - Can you hear the ice cream truck? The Writer's Block Round Table, 2007 (Box 1)
      - Writing redwoods, 2011 (Box 1)
      - Free truth juice The Writer's Block Round Table, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Multiple correctional facilities
      - Honest voices Day, 2001 (Box 1)
      - A crack in the concrete Michigan Prisoners: World Environment, 2005 (Box 1)
      - Writers on the storm: an anthology Spoken Ink Publishing, 2008Creative writing (cont.) (Box 1)
    - Parnall Correctional Facility (Jackson, Mich.)
      - All skinny people must be polite and other thoughts... Creative Writing Workshop, 2005 (Box 1)
      - Beneath the layers: the struggle within The Parnall Poets, 2006 (Box 1)
      - Inappropriate content The Parnall Poets, 2006 (Box 1)
      - Pen light Creative Writing Workshop, 2008 (Box 1)
      - Beyond Frost's mending walls 2010 (Box 1)
    - Parr Highway Correctional Facility (Adrian, Mich.)
      - Just us! Creative Writing Workshop, 2003 (Box 1)
      - When two worlds collide Creative Writing Workshop, 2003 (Box 1)
      - Struggle Creative Writing Workshop, 2003 (Box 1)
      - Eyes sewed shut to hear the best Creative Writing Workshop, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Riverside Correctional Facility (Ionia, Mich.)
      - Pass this on Creative Writing Workshop, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Ryan Correctional Facility (Detroit, Mich.)
      - Broken glass: adapting to the sequence of words, getting new meaning from the things already learned Creative Writing Workshop, 2002 (Box 1)
      - Reflections from the third domain Creative Writing Workshop, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Robert Scott Correctional Facility (Plymouth, Mich.), 2 folders
      - Writing in too small shoes: an anthology of poetry Sisters of Unique Lyrics, 2004 (Box 1)
      - Caged clippings erupt Sisters of Unique Lyrics, 2005 (Box 1)
      - Listen to her life Sisters of Unique Lyrics, [2006] (Box 1)
      - Raw words open pomegranate Sisters of Unique Lyrics, 2006 (Box 1)
      - Swan song: a book of poetry Sisters of Unique Lyrics, 2009 (Box 1)
      - Puzzle Jam unidentified group, undated (Box 1)
    - Southern Michigan Correctional Facility (Jackson, Mich.), 5 folders
      - This is our reality JMF Creative Writing Workshop, 1998 (Box 1)
      - Writings from behind the wall JMF Creative Writing Workshop, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
      - The Poet's Corner Poet's Corner, 2000 (Box 1)
      - The Poet's Beyond. Chapter 3:Journey with us Poet's Corner, 2000 (Box 1)
      - Cities within the cities Creative Writing Workshop, 2000 (Box 1)
      - Book of anthology: poems & short stories JMF Creative Writers Circle, 2001 (Box 1)
      - The new generation of Poet's Corner Poet's Corner, 2001 (Box 1)
      - I'm feeling the heck outta that... Poet's Corner, 2002 (Box 1)
      - The shape of anger Poet's Corner, 2003 (Box 1)
      - Images Poet's Corner, 2004 (Box 1)
      - Arguing with God Poet's Corner, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Thumb Correctional Facility (Lapeer, Mich.)
      - The insides of those on the inside Creative Writing Workshop, 2006 (Box 1)
      - An anthology of poems by the Hibiscus Soldiers, 2006-2007 The Hibiscus Soldiers, 2007 (Box 1)
      - Our writing anthology Creative Writing Workshop, 2008 (Box 1)
      - The gamble of life playbill December 19, 2009 (Box 1)
      - Voices 2011 (Box 1)
    - W. J. Maxey Boys Training School (Whitmore Lake, Mich.) (Box 2)
      - Poets of the millennium Creative Writing Workshop, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Western Wayne Correctional Facility (Plymouth, Mich.)
      - Crazy quilt: an anthology, 2003-2004 Creative Writing Workshop, 2004 (Box 2)
      - Just your imagination Creative Voices, 2004 (Box 2)
    - Unidentified correctional facilities
      - A collection of poems, 1998-2004 Ann Arbor: Prison Creative Arts Project, (2004 ?) (Box 2)
      - Untitled 2005 (Box 2)
      - Writers beyond the block 2008 (Box 2)
      - Spirit's intrepid thoughts 2011-2012 (Box 2)
  - Youth projects
    - Ace Academy-Calumet Center (Highland Park, Mich.)
      - Kings and Queens 2009 (Box 2)
      - Anthology Creative Writing and Spoken Word, 2010 (Box 2)
    - Adrian Training Center (Adrian, Mich.)
      - A great dedication Creative Writing Workshop, 2000 (Box 2)
      - Next anthology: a crucial collection of writings Creative Writing Workshop, 2005 (Box 2)
    - Adrian Training School (Adrian, Mich.)
      - Loving myself Creative Writing Workshop, 2001 (Box 2)
      - From inside an orange ball West Hall Group 1, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Cody College Preparatory Upper School of Teaching (Detroit, Mich.)
      - A book of writing by Cody High School students, Fall 2010 (Box 2)
    - Thomas M. Cooley High School (Detroit, Mich.)
      - Memories: a collection of writings from the Cooley High School Writing Workshop, Creative Writing Workshop, 1998 (Box 2)
      - Getting it off my chest, 1999 (Box 2)
      - Creative Writing Workshop, 1999 (Box 2)
      - Cooley Cardinals Creative Writing Workshop, 2000 (Box 2)
      - "My secret behind closed doors" and "A new beginning" playbill, (2006 ?) (Box 2)
      - Pens, props, plays, and performances playbill 2007 (Box 2)
      - Friday mornings at Cooley Class of 2009 (Box 2)
    - Henry Ford High School (Detroit, Mich.)
      - The book of books: reflections from Henry Ford High School Class of 1998 (Box 2)
    - Southeastern High School (Detroit, Mich.)
      - Poetry and prose reading, 2010 (Box 2)
    - Vista Maria (Dearborn, Mich.), 2 folders
      - Beata Fall 2000 anthology Beata Workshop, 2000 (Box 2)
      - Earthly angels: our anthologie [sic] Delores Hall Creative Writing Workshop, 2001 (Box 2)
      - Girls from D-Hall present: their anthology, a compilation of creative writing and poetry Delores Hall Creative Writing Workshop, 2002 (Box 2)
      - Changing faces: an anthology of songs and poetry Vista Maria Writing Workshop, 2005 (Box 2)
      - Beata Workshop Collective Beata Workshop, 2007-2008 (Box 2)
      - Authentic writers Vista Maria Creative Writing Workshop, 2009 (Box 2)
    - Unidentified projects
      - Girls talkin'-2: poetry 1998 (Box 2)
      - The book of hope, (2004 ?) (Box 2)
      - Life in black and white undated (Box 2)
      - My own flow undated (Box 2)
      - Through our eyes, undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - ArtShow: youth and community development by Shirley Brice Heath and Laura Smyth (Washington, DC: Partners for Livable Communities, c1999 (Box 2)
    - Buzz Alexander by Donna Iadipaolo (Ann Arbor Observer, April 2011) (Box 2)
- Performing Arts
  The Performing Arts series includes programs of mostly theatrical performances that took place in Michigan correctional facilities, training schools and high schools. Select items are programs of poetry readings. A significant number of these the performances took place on the University of Michigan campus. Material is organized into two subseries: Correctional Facilities and Youth Projects, and in alphabetical order by name of institutions within each subseries.
  - Correctional facilities
    - Adrian Training School (Adrian, Mich.) 1994-2006, 2008 (Box 2)
    - Bellamy Creek Correctional Facility (Ionia, Mich.), after 2007 (Box 2)
    - Boysville Correctional Facility (Clinton, Mich.) 1997-2009, 2012 (Box 2)
    - Camp Valley (Ypsilanti, Mich.) 2008, undated (Box 2)
    - Charles Egeler Reception and Guidance Center (Jackson, Mich.) 1993-1998 (Box 2)
    - Cooper Street Correctional Facility (Jackson, Mich.) 2000-, 2013 with gaps (Box 2)
    - Florence Crane Correctional Facility (Coldwater, Mich.) 1991, 1995-2000 (Box 2)
    - G. Robert Cotton Correctional Facility (Jackson, Mich.) 1992, 2002-2008 with gaps and undated (Box 2)
    - Gus Harrison Correctional Facility (Adrian, Mich.) 1995-, 2013 with gaps (Box 2)
    - Huron Center for Boys (Ann Arbor?, Mich.) 1999, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Ionia Maximum Correctional Facility (Ionia, Mich.) 1997, 2007 (Box 2)
    - Macomb Correctional Facility (Lenox, Mich.) 2012 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Reformatory 1997, 2013 (Box 2)
    - Mound Correctional Facility (Detroit, Mich.) 1999-2008 with gaps (Box 2)
    - Parnall Correctional Facility (Jackson, Mich.) 1998-2009 with gaps, undated (Box 2)
    - Parr Highway Correctional Facility (Adrian, Mich.) 2004-2009 with gaps and undated (Box 2)
    - Riverside Correctional Facility (Ionia, Mich.) (Box 2)
    - Robert Scott Correctional Facility (Plymouth, Mich.) 1996-1998, 2004-2009 with gaps (Box 2)
    - Ryan Correctional Facility (Detroit, Mich.) 1995-, 2012 with gaps (Box 2)
    - Saginaw Correctional Facility (Freeland, Mich.) 1997-1999 (Box 2)
    - Southern Michigan Correctional Facility (Jackson, Mich.) 1998-2007 (Box 2)
    - Thumb Correctional Facility (Lapeer, Mich.) 2006-2013 with gaps (Box 2)
    - W. J. Maxey Boys Training School (Whitmore Lake, Mich.) 1995-2013 with gaps (Box 2)
    - Western Wayne Correctional Facility (Plymouth, Mich.) 1995-2004, undated (Box 2)
    - Women's Huron Valley Correctional Facility (Ypsilanti, Mich.) 1997-2013 with gaps (Box 2)
    - Multiple correctional facilities 1995-2006 scattered, and undated (Box 2)
    - Unidentified correctional facilities 1992-2008 scattered, and undated (Box 2)
  - Youth Projects
    - ACE Academy (Calumet Center and Lincoln Center, Highland Park, Mich.) 2005-2009, 2012-2013 (Box 2)
    - Catherine Ferguson Academy (Detroit, Mich.) 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - Central High School (Detroit, Mich.) 2012 (Box 2)
    - Cody High School (Detroit, Mich.) 2011-2012 (Box 2)
    - Detroit International Academy for Young Women (Detroit, Mich.) 2012-2013 (Box 2)
    - Henry Ford High School (Detroit, Mich.) 1995-2008 with gaps and undated (Box 2)
    - Mumford High School (Detroit, Mich.) 2013 (Box 2)
    - Northwestern High School (Detroit, Mich.) 2013 (Box 2)
    - Phoenix High School (Kalamazoo, Mich.) 1996 (Box 2)
    - Southeastern High School (Detroit, Mich.) 1999-2001, undated (Box 2)
    - Spectrum Juvenile Justice Services (Westland, Mich.) 2012 (Box 2)
    - Thomas M. Cooley High School (Detroit, Mich.) 1998-2009 with gaps and undated (Box 2)
    - Vista Maria (Dearborn, Mich.) 1997-2012 with gaps (Box 2)
    - Unidentified 2012 (Box 2)
- Prison Creative Arts Project Material
  The Prison Creative Arts Project Material series includes the project's newsletter (2010-2013, incomplete set), articles about the project and about Buzz Alexander, as well as assorted PCAP benefit events programs.
  - ArtShow: youth and community development by Shirley Brice Heath and Laura Smyth (Washington, DC: Partners for Livable Communities, c1999) (Box 3)
  - Benefits 1999-2004 scattered years (Box 3)
  - Buzz Alexander by Donna Iadipaolo (Ann Arbor Observer, April 2011) (Box 3)
  - Newsletter 2010-2013, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - PCAP programs (listing) 1999-2009 (Box 3)
- Audiovisual Material
  The Audio Visual material series includes DVDs with theatrical productions recorded between 1994 and 2013. The productions created by male and female groups of inmates and relate to their background and prison experience. Production titles and dates were taken from the disc labels. Also included DVDs documenting art and opening receptions of ten Annual Exhibitions of Art by Michigan Prisoners that took place between 1996 and 2012. "Junkie," performed by The Sisters Within Theater Troupe (6 GB) is available online.
  - Puddin's Place, Sisters Within Theater Troup, May 12, 1987 (Box 3)
  - A time when..., Western Wayne Players, April 1992 (Box 3)
  - Junkie Sisters Within Theater Troupe, November 21, 1992
  - Inside and personal, Sisters Within Theater Troupe, May 21, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Willie's corner, Western Wayne Players, December 8-9, 1994 (Box 3)
  - 17, Sisters Within Theater Troupe, March 26, 1995 (Box 3)
  - First and second annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners, February 1996, February 11, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Best friends: struggling to succeed, Sisters Within Theater Troupe, June 29, 1996 (Box 3)
  - In the ghetto Western Wayne Players, February 18, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Florence Crane Sisters Within Theater Troupe, December 13, 1997 (Box 3)
  - The Kidney of a King, Western Wayne Players, January 1998 (Box 3)
  - Third annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners February 10-25, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Unfinished business Sisters Within Theater Troupe, December 20, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Fourth annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners February 9-24, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Fifth annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners February 8-23, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Sixth annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners February 6-22, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Seventh annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners March 5-18, 2002 (Box 3)
  - Eighth annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners 2003 (Box 3)
  - Ninth annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners March 2-16, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Tenth annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners March 22-April 5, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Hearts in all the right places, Sisters Within Theater Troupe, August 17, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Eleventh annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners 2006 (Box 3)
  - Twelfth annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners 2007 (Box 3)
  - Thirteenth annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners 2008 (Box 3)
  - Fifteenth annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners March 24-April 8, 2009 (Box 3)
  - Within-the-sisters within Sisters Within Theater Troupe, February 2010 (Box 3)
  - 2 Plays Cooley High School Autistic Youth, April 2010 (Box 3)
  - Seventeenth annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners March-April 2012 (Box 3)
  - Eighteenth annual exhibition of art by Michigan prisoners March 24-April 8, 2013 (Box 3)
  - Family values: a tale of love & support Gentlemen of Cooper Street, April 25, 2013 (Box 3)